hi everyone it's cohort three and August
1st
we're in our second discussion on
chapter nine
so
if either of you would like before we
jump into some specific questions
are are there any general comments or
any other topics that that people want
to address
otherwise we will uh probably look
through some answers and curate and
improve some some discourse
yep nothing for me
all right I I added some questions at
the end but we can go through the other
stuff first
perfect okay
and esmail thank you for your question
um
what does this text mean about epistemic
value
so so
let me know if it's okay to modify the
question to what what is epistemic value
if if that's what your question was or
let me know
okay
let us uh
you added some of the new questions at
the at the bottom here Neil
yeah that's right all right
it's it's one sort of
big question really
um
which one Let's Do It
um in a non-metronization so that one
and then all right awesome yeah all
right let's start here
all right so
so my take on on the chapter is
it's it's trying to fit
active inference into a a framework of
of what science is
um
the the new thing I think the the big
idea for me
was the metabasian
inference which I understand is trying
to make uh
a so
you know someone's trying to make
inferences about something
has itself got beliefs
um so maybe I I don't know if I've got
that
right
um
so so the first part of that question is
is what does
what does this have chapter have to
contribute when that isn't the case
if if we're just trying to use it to
understand
something that can be modeled
um
and then
uh
the second part is what the
um
the chapter talks about is is thinking
about it in the context of brains uh so
Psychiatry but it presumably can be
applied to anything in which
the the system that's being modeled
and in any way be said to be
of having beliefs
uh and I've I've mentioned then it's
intentional stance there where we you
know we're not
uh
necessarily believing you know we don't
think any there's any sentience there so
you can think of
we could talk about a thermostat
thinking it's too hot
so uh without actually saying
anything about any sort of mental
processes going on there
um so so it seems to me that
the metabase in aspect uh could
potentially be saying we could
potentially be useful for
for
for this so beyond Psychiatry psychology
uh
yeah and it's so then skipping over the
third question was this question is well
is this actually being applied in you
know outside of Neuroscience
and psychology it seems particularly
uh
what I thought be useful to be including
it in behavioral economics
uh and
and maybe in systems engineering I don't
know
great great questions we'll we'll start
with the first ones
up ready to go
oh oh okay I I see the second one was
here
also welcome Molly
okay
thanks
and uh
I I put the link but
this uh upload of the textbook
did a little this is a good starting
point
um
all right
so the first thing that that
uh
well
let's just start by recalling the The
Meta Bayesian
um
approach
in nine nine point
one
so I think you summarized it perfectly
Neil
were doing Bayesian inference about
something that has beliefs
so it the aboutness of the subjective
model
is the environment
which may be the laboratory or or the
niche
um and and thus the aboutness of the
scientific model
is the rat and the Maze which has an a
model that has an aboutness of the maze
so that's this kind of like
nested or meta Bayesian approach we're
using Bayesian approaches from the
outside
but then when we when we get to the good
stuff it is also
a Bayesian model
with an aboutness of an environment
um so I I think this is a great way to
put it
trying to make inferences about
something that has it beliefs or or
trying to make inference about something
that does inference
so your first question was what does the
chapter contribute when that is not the
case
here I believe we can return to our
favorite path integrals
paper
and point to the continuum
where on the sophisticated end of the
spectrum
we have a situation like that in this
figure
where
um you know here's us as scientists here
at the blanket States
are the solid line
and then we're inferring
a cognitive model through for example
structure learning or or some other
um uh a priori constraints
we're inferring the cognitive model
that's that's looking back onto the
outside
so so The metabasian Stance is
required
in the cognitive on cognitive setting
just to be clear that that to model
another cognitive entity outside of the
metabasing stance I I'm not exactly sure
what what the alternative approach would
be but you asked what do we get when
this is not the case
um
you could model and and and inert
um system
accordingly here
for example maybe here you know it's a
light switch or something and it just it
just it doesn't have any action
selection of its own or it's like inner
or it's a passive inference object
so what do we gain
we gain continuity with those cases
thus grounding cognitive Sciences
we can discuss this more but but that to
me feels like the big
home run
is continuity
along this continuum
of of uh sophistication
from absolutely inert particles
on through arbitrarily complex cognitive
entities
so it's not to say that it's going to be
uniquely explanatory or or of a
predictive value it may be like getting
on an extra apparatus that you don't
necessarily meet
which would be the same thing as saying
um you could have just started with a
simpler model because you're bringing
out this big apparatus that's just
condensing down to a simpler model
so
do do any of you think of any other
advantages that are gained
actually where so where is that that
figure from
figure two that that paper
right
okay
thank you
so it's creating it's creating a
scaffolding for the observational
encounter
that allows us to have system of
Interest
along this continuity
it's absolutely required here you might
be able to get away with a simpler
perspective
in a simpler setting
but this is the most expressive way that
we can dial it up arbitrarily
um complicated and also dial it back
down
like maybe this just is a single node in
this computational graph
it just observations get passed in
there's a single node and then it gets
passed out
but
this Frame but but the the scientists
lab doesn't have to change whether
they're studying the metronome
um or the bird
yeah
and I I I I agree that it's important to
connect it to these uh
like to the standard stages the
scientific process Ali or anyone else
want to just add more
yeah if I may add some other comments
about uh but of course I didn't hear the
question from the beginning but uh from
what I heard uh you see I I believe it's
uh essential to
um always clarify our Concepts and
definitions in terms of what we're
really talking about when we talk about
uh Agency on one hand
um I don't know uh cognition or
Consciousness or whatever because all of
these terms
they have lots of
um baggage coming along with them so we
need to be careful uh what exactly we
mean by agency or in this case I want to
emphasize more on agency because this is
quite a controversial term because as we
know uh in the at least in the
mainstream biology
people don't want to bestow Agency on uh
inert objects or even some simple
quote-unquote simple organism but on the
other hand there are some mechanical and
naturalistic definitions of agency and
Welsh's Theory or from fap and so on
I I don't know if you've seen this uh
nice article by Philip ballg called from
a couple of months ago organisms as
agents of evolution uh in this
pretty much non-technical essay he
overviews some of the conceptions about
agencies and he also
I think uh yeah
he he has mentioned fep
quite an extensive detail I mean
comparatively but the the case here I
mean Ball's case is that we still don't
know how to model agency as
naturalistically as uh I don't know some
physical phenomena so of course there
are possibilities to model agency these
as purely
physical
trajectory threes or
um
probably to think about and see but I
think the point here I want to make is
that this is not exactly what we uh
always think when we try to trace the
path of a physical system through a
state space we don't usually think of I
don't know simple particle or an inert
object as following a path of
um or following a goal-directed motion
right but on the other hand there was
this recent
interesting interview
Sean Carroll's and Sean Carroll's
mindscape podcast with David krakauer
and it was quite quite an interesting
podcast because For the First Time I I
heard a definition of complex systems as
something that can be directly be
applied to fep you know namely he
defined complex systems or even the
complexity signs as the study of
teleonomic matter right so obviously
what he meant by teleonomic matter
doesn't have anything to do with
I don't know
uh
material or the black
man or pity
these
but
come along agents
see
they HP through
that
[Music]
The Rock
some weenies
uh
[Music]
this one
sorry Ali it just it just it's through
the suspected 80.
uh sorry just okay can you hear me now
yeah just just back up to um chileanomic
systems it's not not an extra material
cause it's what
okay uh so uh yeah it allows for uh the
definition of agency through a while to
hold spectrum that encompasses uh both
in Earth objects or simple organisms up
to the most complex phenomenon we know
of the uh of in the whole universe
namely the human brain uh so this
defining characteristic of complex
systems as a teleonomic matter I believe
uh is a is quite an essential move here
because uh this is
this can be seen as some of the
underlying assertions of fep as well
because
um the same mathematical technology it I
mean if we take Bayesian mechanics as uh
something that can be applied both to a
simple physical phenomena and to
um I don't know Consciousness or a
cognition or agency or whatever then we
need to uh Define some uh
some essential parameter that can be
um put in put on to and put onto
continuous Spectrum without
um on the one hand limiting too much uh
and on the other without uh I mean
without including or limiting too much
so uh yeah these recent moves uh in uh
both complexity science and some of the
recent advances in biology uh seems
interestingly
convergent with some of the assertions
of fep and I hope in the future uh some
interesting unifying perspectives uh can
be gleaned from uh seeing these kinds of
inter connectedness and interrelation
between all of these theories and
specifically by by looking at how we
Define agency in the most
naturalistically and
mechanistic mechanistic way possible
nice great it's like saying like we
can't have a framework that has a
continuity of ice and liquid and gaseous
water
it's like well it's not saying that
there's not face differences
but we want to have something that that
like you said doesn't over include or
under include
and doesn't appeal to extra material
or extra systemic factors except
credibly
and then if we if we
um create that
uh
measure
then
we can we can um talk about the agency
of
um
different systems
okay so I hope
but but you know in your question you
wrote other than unifying ideas into a
common framework so
maybe one response is little other than
that but that's the big deal
um yeah I mean it's it's so it's a big
deal for me it's yeah it's it's a
beautiful yeah it fits in yeah a nice
bigger picture
um
and I yeah I feel as though as
you know I've got a lot of a lot of
things that could come out of of that
framework
thinking about it but it's it's not
apparent to me what that is
at the moment
yeah I I mean there's
um even just the the concept that some
people may walk around uh feeling and
projecting that there's a a difference
between uh a difference in kinds income
measurability difference between like
systems that compute or don't or
cognitive systems or not agentic systems
or not
adaptive systems or not sentient systems
um it's like well again we can have ice
and liquid
so it's not like we're we're we're we're
neutering our capacity to distinguish
systems
literally the opposite
proponents I'm not even saying anyone
specifically is but just just um
allegorically proponents of income
measurability
are actually stymieing their own
capacity to compare scientifically
they may be able to perform
qualitative comparison which is totally
legitimate it is what it is though
but you cannot have quantitative
comparison
now it may not be as simple simple as
like a scalar number
and I think that's kind of the open
space with um category Theory and
different kinds of equality and sameness
but we need to at least have the
articulations and and the framework just
to scaffold these kinds of systems
otherwise we're just begging for there
to be a different framework
I mean if this was the periodic table
could we want a different framework for
different
particles or I I I'm sure we can think
of other ways of where this brings a lot
of unity
um
okay next question that you added
uh metabasian inference maybe can be
applied to any understanding any system
of interest in which the subject can be
considered having beliefs and intentions
then it's intentional stance yeah it
including into the the even you have a
thermostat
um but but but not uh not just a
thermostat here as a thermostat coupled
to an actor actuator unit because you
said it can act but you could say that
that yeah yeah a heating system
um but this this intentional stance goes
even below where most of the intentional
stance people would probably feel
comfortable saying like that rock just
wants to be there hmm
yeah and so it's like but that's not
intention it's like that's what I'm
saying yeah but either you're gonna
Grant there to be a Continuum of
intentionality
and then I think
um then whether that's realism is there
really a Continuum of intentionality
take it or leave it but can we approach
systems with a Continuum of
intentionality
absolutely and that at least
topologically has to have a structure
like this
you could have a different
um model architecture inside of here
um but that model architecture doesn't
even have to be what what we would
consider necessarily A cognitive model
why couldn't this be um
uh biological variables and here's the
health record and then here's the
outcomes of Health
so this is even more General than
cognitive modeling
per se
because rather it's just describing the
informational relationship
between the modeler and the models
up to and including systems where the
models
has an aboutness of the laboratory or of
the communication itself
um what's the relationship between
agency and belief because you could have
that
subjective model that has that could be
said to have beliefs
but it might not have agency it might
just be medical records for example
but those medical records could be said
to embody a belief that
the the patient has whatever
diagnosis
um
yeah that's I I am sure both agency and
belief
have copious
um
like literature and and semantics
just off the off the cuff belief having
more to do with what we would associate
with the perceptual sense making side of
active inference and agency having to do
more with the um
policy selection
aspects
like
and policy selection
entailing uh sentient or adaptive policy
selection
entailing some belief architecture you
could have something that exhibits a lot
of agency and has like minimal beliefs
like it's just like flailing or babbling
or thrashing
potentially
so it's it's exerting
efficacy
which under some definitions of agency
may qualify
with limited belief potentially no
Justified true belief
whereas in their kind of highest
marriage we're talking about like
beliefs about action planning as
inference
those kinds of areas
the agency implies action on the
environment I think I mean as you say
policies it's it's
performing some action you know that can
then help it learn as opposed to you can
have something that just forms beliefs
and that's just something doing passive
inference
um
is active model-based analysis actually
being applied
in areas outside of neuro
uh psychop uh psychopathy or
psychopathology
behavioral economic economic systems
engineering so definitely we can bring
in some some papers by Henriksen on um
cognitive economics now not all
cognitive economics is utilizing active
inference
[Music]
um
but some are
this name it sounds familiar and I
believe it may be using active inference
little
but some
um industrial systems engineering
yes
uh well robotics another area
um
industrial systems engineering
ranging from the most logistical and
operational
like what verses and others are involved
in
uh on through like what um Stephen Fox
is involved in
with uh
um
social organization
so here's this then here we have the
Stephen Fox John boyick
angle
with socio-technical systems
um
Niagara ecology in fact I I I'm gonna
I'm gonna go to another
um this this is a little little peep
into our uh
into our our open source ecosystems
document
um which of course Ali and and Neil
you're welcome to be authors on just
just uh email me if you if you don't
have the information that you feel like
you need
um
this is our citation train I think we
went from we go from yeah literally
citation 7 to 99 so it's kind of a
monster cognitive neuroscience and
cognitive philosophy artificial
intelligence and AI explainability
robotics human health clinical
Psychiatry social developmental
psychology social sciences
mathematical physics physics of life
Consciousness studies phenomenology
evolutionary ecology and development
cyber and cognitive security mapping and
modeling of information ecosystems
ontology modeling and maintenance
rhetorical analysis Logistics and
business intelligence theoretical and
Applied Biology and ecology project
management and team science Collective
Behavior military science
if there are some other domains um we
will literally add them in fact we
probably should add
[Music]
um
uh
economics
um I know that we cite some though but
also I'll just write social sciences and
economics
any thoughts on this um list
or or like what other domains would be
exciting for you to see
that's your education
I I'm just gonna I'm just gonna copy it
into the chat too yeah that's too long
it's too long I mean uh but just uh
I'm gonna copy the uh
uh the document there but but yeah of
course we're the textbook groups I'm not
gonna go down the rabbit hole with the
open source ecosystems but um that's
that's exactly what we've been thinking
about
and and also we didn't even like cite
digital Gaia versus and so on
so
um or thought Forge or any of our other
um colleagues in industry
um
and that's kind of the idea with the
ecosystem we have people who are working
more on the theory and then it's not
always so visible necessarily where the
applications are happening but I think
we can do a lot of work to improve
like the discoverability
and connect you know use the ontology to
connect across
settings and cases there's there's just
a lot but again another conversation
all right
all right um
esmail asked what is epistemic value
let's see where it comes up in um
chapter nine otherwise we can look look
to an earlier chapter
as well
yeah epistemic values primarily
discussed in in chapter seven
Ali wanna what's your take on on
epistemic value and Nails well just let
let's just get some uh looking from
chapter nine looking back to seven what
is epistemic value
okay so epistemic value is uh one of the
a key terminology of active inference
which is also in parallel with
um I mean
practical value because you see
sometimes uh when an agent
tries to infer its best course of action
within an environment it's not always a
trade-off between
um I mean
the thing that
or it's it's not a a necessary trade-off
between survival and also the minimum
the explore exploit phenomena so for
example in some of the cases the agent
needs to somehow gather information
about the environment and it and it
actually prefers Gathering the
information about the environment and
the the situation in which it resides uh
in order to take more
um suitable actions uh for it to to
preserve its persistence through time uh
or in other words it's survival uh so
epistemic value is what uh gives
um a kind of numerical value to this
kind of exploring uh the environment and
also
how we can use this numerical uh value
uh in a trade-off between what we gain
in uh what what we gain informationally
about the environment and the course of
actions we take through within that
environment so
sometimes it acts as a central essential
goal or purpose for the agent to
increase its epistemic value through its
seek information seeking actions rather
than just changing the environment in
order to better fit its generative model
nice thank you
Neil what's your take
oh you're muted if you're adding
anything or all
sorry I was yeah
um
yeah I was thinking when I was talking
I we think I I think of the this anxiety
exploration exploitation
um so in reinforcement learning uh it's
it's very much
uh
exploration is is for direct impact on
the policy
um but we as humans go through life
collecting information that and storing
it
um
with likely
um no future use of it so you could say
we we're epistemic we do epistemic
Gathering
of stuff that has no
apparent epistemic value but
circumstances might change and it might
become
valuable
um so I don't know if there's a
distinction to be made between
Well yeah if bringing in this idea of
value
of knowledge
yeah that that's a very interesting
point about like the pure value of
information
at least with respect to its role in
decision making
like if we're thinking about people
using social media applications and so
on or or um or or or who knows what else
maybe even um
uh
uh just the the desire to to flip every
rock over see if there's an ant colony
underneath there like there are um
uh expected free energy being composed
of pragmatic and epistemic value
gives us extreme flexibility
to Model A diversity of of settings and
cases
so this is summarized in um figure 2.6
on the left of the main equation we have
pragmatic value
which is how surprising observations are
with respect to preferences
and on the right side we have the larger
epistemic value
which is a KL Divergence
hence can be attracted practically
optimized in the variational Bayesian
framework
and
um
three
and five are identical
whereas two and four differ
and specifically
four brings in the observations as a
conditioned upon that specific policy
being enumerated or calculated for
expected free energy
so under a policy
where the observations are not expected
to to add any value
in terms of reducing uncertainty that
policy
is not assigned a high epistemic value
it may have a high pragmatic value or
not
whereas a sequence of observations that
a given policy provides
which do cause a Divergence from what is
what is understood other than through
that action being taken that would be
informative again that may positive or A
A detrimental pragmatic value like
what's like I wonder what would happen
if I did this
but that may threaten homeostasis but
having epistemic and pragmatic value
Unified
under a singular decision-making
imperative
allows us to find these previously
unappreciated Concepts
um in in a uh to to be under the
umbrella
of expected free energy which we utilize
for policy selection
but most briefly epistemic values the
value of incoming information
in terms of observations
about hidden States
reducing uncertainty about the hidden
States
chapter 7 deals with it more
one interesting question maybe for the
future is like how is epistemic value
treated differently in the discrete and
in the continuous case
like do you need explicit planning
discrete potentially maybe even
symbolized planning
in order to truly engage with the
counterfactual
value of information
so how do we how do we um
think about the epistemic value of
continuous activity
like groping I mean opt there might be a
connection to Optimal grasp
and groping around in a sort of
continuous reflexive way to to gain a
grip on an object
but with that load on pragmatic value
where optimal grip is preferred
and or without load on epistemic value
where how to achieve optimal grasp or
what it would feel like to have optimal
grasp is not known
what are the two related reasons for
fitting a computational model to
observed Behavior I believe this is an
exact quote
Let's uh
okay
let's see how well perplexity.ai does
it's going to have to context switch a
little bit it's going to have to change
languages but we all do
I think this is also which more and more
uh synthetic intelligences are gonna now
it's asking us us a question
now how would it evaluate all the
questions that it could ask us
which one should ask well
active inference
how will it know what question to ask
what path of action is going to be most
relevant
okay here we go
here we go
first estimate parameters of Interest
in terms of computational phenotyping
the second is to compare alternative
hypotheses
so like to give an example from from
botany
um
the first one
would be like we have a bunch of strains
of corn
and we want to know which one has a
different growth rate
computational phenotyping
the second one would be like does corn
growth rate depend on just humidity or
humidity and genotype or humidity
genotype and temperature
so the first one is parameter estimation
computational phenotyping is parameter
estimation and the second reason the
comparison of alternative hypotheses
is model comparison
the synthetic intelligence here has
provided uh
a difference
set of answers that aren't aren't aren't
um
terrible
and it can't necessarily answer
perfectly from the textbook
anyways
9.1
wow
Ollie this looks like somewhat of a
little side jury
I don't remember it but it seems like it
happens
foundationalists
coherentists infinitists
that's good to have
about that
this goes beyond proof of principle
simulations we have seen in previous
chapters instead exploits active
inference in answering scientific
questions what does that mean
this is a pretty concise answer previous
chapters generated the model
and played around with it
EG used it to generate
plausible data
now we are building the Machinery to
take in real data and fit that to
data
and and fit that data to a model
to slash with the model
two uses
on page 174.
map territory fallacy
not a full question how does this work
okay how does the work connect with map
territory fallacy in the context of
chapter nine being about data analysis
does the work commit the map territory
fallacy or rather help us articulate or
evade being fallacious
so let's think about figure 9.1
some have criticized fep by implying or
suggesting it's guilty of making a
fallacy that the map is the territory
I mean
citations needed
Also regarding generative process and
generative model uh we actually spoke
with Maxwell or in a scientific Advisory
board meeting
it was really funny
and of course
um Illuminating of high epistemic value
here's what he added this morning
I I of course pointed to Ali's
uh question during the uh
inner screen stream
and he said there's one generative model
it's the system level description it's
our model of the whole environment agent
system it is the entire causal
connective tissue it's a joint density
of the real model of the dependencies of
the system
if the generative model contains a
Markov blanket via sparcity and it does
then you get an additional density the
variational density
where internal states parameterize with
an aboutness of external States and
those internal States will look like
they are tracking external things
in the sense of the generalized
synchrony
generative process refers to the
Dynamics that give rise to observations
that are hard coded in
and so he analogized that to the
Newton's Laws
it is not the case that the generative
model is a model of the generative
process
philosophers are comfortable with
approaches like the helmholtz in the
Bolton machine and from there arose the
distinction between the recognition and
the generative density the tail to
densities
but that is not the sense in which
generative model is being used here
so just kind of a fun
update to an ongoing discussion
and Carl was there
ends
endorsed and approved
well
time flies
time flies like an arrow fruit flies
like a banana
as the famous quote said
we are at the end of chapter nine now
in the coming weeks we will be heading
into chapter 10.
then after two weeks on the uh text and
concept heavy chapter 10 we will be
closing
this cohort
so it's very exciting
presumably after this
we will
um
wrap the transcripts of cohort one two
and three
and publish those three
together
anyone have any closing thoughts
good session all right next next time
chapter 10 looks good
awesome yep totally looking forward to
it
all right
thank you fellas till next time
thanks cheers bye